<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:amn="https://www.amnesty.org/en/">

<channel>
	<title>Amnesty International</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.amnesty.org/en</link>
	<description>Inspiring people against injustice to bring the world closer to human rights &#38; dignity enjoyed by all.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 17:49:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

		<item>
		<title>Indonesia: Government should investigate shooting of children in Intan Jaya, Papua</title>
		<link>https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/indonesia-government-should-investigate-shooting-of-children-in-intan-jaya-papua/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amnesty International]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 09:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<amn:content-types>
			<amn:id name="News">1148</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2181</amn:id>
		</amn:content-types>
		<amn:topics>
			<amn:id name="Armed Conflict">2063</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Armed Groups">2064</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Children">2071</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Discrimination">2081</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Killings and Disappearances">2118</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Unlawful Killings">2119</amn:id>
		</amn:topics>
		<amn:countries>
			<amn:id name="Asia and the Pacific">1697</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Indonesia">1818</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="South East Asia and the Pacific">1710</amn:id>
		</amn:countries>
		<amn:resource-types>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2143</amn:id>
		</amn:resource-types>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.amnesty.org/en/?p=142359</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Two children were shot, one fatally, during a gunfight between armed groups and Indonesian security forces in Intan Jaya regency, Papua province Local residents told Amnesty International they believed shots came from nearby military command post Hundreds of residents fled to churches The Indonesian government should promptly, thoroughly, independently, transparently and effectively investigate the death [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/indonesia-government-should-investigate-shooting-of-children-in-intan-jaya-papua/">Indonesia: Government should investigate shooting of children in Intan Jaya, Papua</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul><li><strong><em>Two children were shot, one fatally, during a gunfight between armed groups and Indonesian security forces in Intan Jaya regency, Papua province</em></strong></li><li><strong><em>Local residents told Amnesty International they believed shots came from nearby military command post</em></strong></li><li><strong><em>Hundreds of residents fled to churches</em></strong></li></ul>



<p>The Indonesian government should promptly, thoroughly, independently, transparently and effectively investigate the death of one child and the injury to another after two children were shot amid a gunfight between armed groups and Indonesian security forces in Intan Jaya regency, Papua Province, said Amnesty International today.&nbsp;<br><br>Amnesty International talked to seven persons about the recent gunfight in Intan Jaya regency. They said that one of the victims, a two-year-old child, died hours after the shooting. The sources also told Amnesty International that they believed the shots that struck the victims came from the direction of a nearby military command post.&nbsp;<br><br>“Authorities must conduct a prompt, thorough, independent, transparent and effective investigation into the shooting,” said Amnesty International’s Indonesia Executive Director Usman Hamid.&nbsp;<br><br>“Anyone suspected to be responsible must be brought to justice in fair trial. Authorities must ensure access to justice and effective remedies for the victims and their families.”<br><br><strong>Children caught up in gunfight&nbsp;</strong><br><br>The two children were shot during a gunfight between Indonesian security forces and armed groups on the evening of 26 October 2021.&nbsp;<br><br>Local sources told Amnesty International that the victims were at home in a residential area near the Koramil (military command) post in Sugapa district when the shooting took place. The Koramil post is situated in an elevated area, while the houses are about 200 metres away on lower ground.&nbsp;<br><br>One of the victims, a two-year old child (NS), was hit in the stomach. Photos obtained by Amnesty International show a bullet wound in the child’s stomach. According to local sources, he died the following morning. The second victim, a six-year-old child, was shot in the back. Amnesty International obtained photos showing the injury.<br><br>The two children were reportedly brought to the local health unit immediately after being shot, but they did not receive medical treatment because no health workers were present. Local sources told Amnesty International that the six-year-old survivor is currently in hospital.<br><br>Local sources have expressed concern that Indonesian military forces may have entered the residential area to seek retribution after a soldier was injured in a shootout with an armed group in the area earlier on Tuesday. According to monitoring by Amnesty International, when a shootout between the military and Papuan armed groups results in military casualties, security forces often seek out members of armed groups in nearby residential areas, which often results in civilian deaths.&nbsp;</p>


<blockquote class="blockquote is-lined" style='quotes:"“" "”" "‘" "’"'><p>The government should protect civilian lives, including children, during security operations and provide medical and humanitarian assistance to those affected</p>
<cite>Richard Pearshouse</cite></blockquote>


<p><br>The Papuan police claimed on Wednesday that the two children were shot by an armed group while they were outside their homes.&nbsp;<br><br>The situation in Sugapa district remains tense. Local sources told Amnesty International that the gunfight between armed groups and Indonesian security forces started on Monday evening (25 October) and continued on 29 October. As the conflict escalated, hundreds of villagers in Intan Jaya fled their homes to churches.&nbsp;<br><br>“The government should protect civilian lives, including children, during security operations and provide medical and humanitarian assistance to those affected,” said Richard Pearshouse, Head of Crisis and Environment for Amnesty International.&nbsp;<br><br><strong>The intensification of conflict in Intan Jaya</strong><br><br>This incident is the most recent civilian casualty in a wider intensification of armed conflict in Intan Jaya over the last two years.&nbsp;<br><br>Since early October 2021, Sem Kobogau, a civilian resident in Sugapa district, has been missing. Local media reported that Sem Kobogau was arrested by four TNI (Indonesian military) members on 5 October 2021.&nbsp;<br><br>In September 2020, Rev. Yeremia Zanambani, a 68-year-old senior pastor in Intan Jaya, was allegedly shot, stabbed and killed by an Indonesian soldier. The National Commission on Human Rights’ investigations stated that members of the military were involved in the killing. The authorities have conducted an autopsy on his body, but are yet to announce the result. Yeremia’s family are demanding that the case be brought to Indonesia’s human rights court. A criminal investigation into the killing, however, has stalled for nearly a year.<br><br>“The increasing number of civilian casualties shows that the current approach is clearly ineffective in maintaining security in Papua,” said Usman Hamid.&nbsp;&nbsp;<br><br>“We urge the government to reconsider its security tactics in Papua to end the cycle of violence that has caused so many civilian deaths.”</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/indonesia-government-should-investigate-shooting-of-children-in-intan-jaya-papua/">Indonesia: Government should investigate shooting of children in Intan Jaya, Papua</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
      
      
      
      		<item>
		<title>Iraq: Yezidi reparations law progress welcome, but more must be done to assist survivors</title>
		<link>https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/iraq-yezidi-reparations-law-progress-welcome-but-more-must-be-done-to-assist-survivors/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amnesty International]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 08:58:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<amn:content-types>
			<amn:id name="News">1148</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2181</amn:id>
		</amn:content-types>
		<amn:topics>
			<amn:id name="Armed Conflict">2063</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Armed Groups">2064</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Children">2071</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Impunity">2102</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Sexual Rights">2093</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Sexual Violence">2113</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="War Crimes and Crimes Against Humanity">2066</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Women's Rights">2083</amn:id>
		</amn:topics>
		<amn:countries>
			<amn:id name="Iraq">2029</amn:id>
		</amn:countries>
		<amn:resource-types>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2143</amn:id>
		</amn:resource-types>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.amnesty.org/en/?p=136756</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>New regulations passed by Iraq’s parliament in September on the Yazidi Survivors Law mark long-overdue progress for many who suffered atrocities committed by the Islamic State (IS) armed group, Amnesty International said. However, the Iraqi authorities must do more to address the needs of all survivors, including by specifically providing reparations for children who were [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/iraq-yezidi-reparations-law-progress-welcome-but-more-must-be-done-to-assist-survivors/">Iraq: Yezidi reparations law progress welcome, but more must be done to assist survivors</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>New regulations passed by Iraq’s parliament in September on the Yazidi Survivors Law mark long-overdue progress for many who suffered atrocities committed by the Islamic State (IS) armed group, Amnesty International said.</p>



<p>However, the Iraqi authorities must do more to address the needs of all survivors, including by specifically providing reparations for children who were born as a result of sexual violence by IS members during captivity.</p>



<p>The Iraqi authorities also largely ignored the significant <a href="https://c4jr.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/01092021_C4JR-Media-Statement-ENGLISH.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">recommendations</a> made by Iraqi civil society organizations on the regulations, meaning they lack a survivor-centred approach and fail to establish accountable mechanisms and processes for outreach, applications and review of claims.</p>


<blockquote class="blockquote align-start is-lined" style='quotes:"“" "”" "‘" "’"'><p>The new regulations to enact the Yazidi Survivors Law are an essential step towards justice for the Yezidi community, and towards ensuring that reparations actually reach survivors</p>
<cite>Nicolette Waldman, Researcher in Amnesty International’s Crisis Response Programme</cite></blockquote>


<p>“The new regulations to enact the Yazidi Survivors Law are an essential step towards justice for the Yezidi community, and towards ensuring that reparations actually reach survivors,” said Nicolette Waldman, Researcher in Amnesty International’s Crisis Response Programme.</p>



<p>“However, children who were born as a result of sexual violence by IS members are not specifically referenced in the law, and nor are the needs of their mothers. This is a significant omission which must be addressed to ensure justice for all Yezidi survivors.</p>



<p>“Although some Yezidi women chose to separate from children who were born of sexual violence, many others were forcibly separated – and remain desperate to be reunited.</p>



<p>“The Iraqi authorities must address the plight of these women and children by explicitly including in reparations children born of sexual violence, and taking all necessary actions to ensure these women and children can live together in safety.</p>



<p>“The organizations and civil society actors whose tireless advocacy has helped the law become reality are to be commended. Unfortunately, the Iraqi authorities missed a key opportunity to incorporate their recommendations on the regulations of the law. At Amnesty International, we now call on the Iraqi authorities to heed their calls during the actual implementation of the law.”</p>



<p>Between 2014 and 2017, IS committed atrocities against the Yezidi community in Iraq amounting to war crimes and crimes against humanity, and, according to a&nbsp; UN inquiry, genocide.</p>



<h2 id="h-background">Background</h2>



<p>On 1 March 2021, the Iraqi parliament passed the Yazidi Survivors Law which provides a reparations framework for many survivors of IS crimes, including women and girls who were subjected to sexual violence, as well as child survivors who were abducted before the age of 18.</p>



<p>Although the law focuses on the Yezidi community, it also includes in its scope reparations for survivors from the Christian, Turkmen, and Shabak minority groups. The law provides for a monthly salary, a plot of land or housing unit, support to re-enter school, access to psychosocial and other health services, as well as other essential assistance.<strong></strong></p>



<p>In a report released last year, <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2020/07/iraq-yezidi-child-survivors-of-islamic-state-facing-unprecedented-health-crisis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amnesty International documented</a> how almost 2,000 Yezidi children who have returned to their families after being held captive by IS are facing a physical and mental health crisis.<strong></strong></p>



<p>The report,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/mde14/2759/2020/en/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Legacy of Terror: The Plight of Yezidi Child Survivors of ISIS,</em></a>&nbsp;also addressed the urgent need to end the forced separation of Yezidi women and their children born of sexual violence by IS members.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/iraq-yezidi-reparations-law-progress-welcome-but-more-must-be-done-to-assist-survivors/">Iraq: Yezidi reparations law progress welcome, but more must be done to assist survivors</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
      
      
      		<item>
		<title>Nicaragua: International organizations set out five reasons why elections do not guarantee the exercise of human rights</title>
		<link>https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/nicaragua-five-reasons-why-elections-do-not-guarantee-the-exercise-of-human-rights/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amnesty International]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 17:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<amn:content-types>
			<amn:id name="News">1148</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2181</amn:id>
		</amn:content-types>
		<amn:countries>
			<amn:id name="Americas">1699</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Central America and the Caribbean">1705</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Nicaragua">1793</amn:id>
		</amn:countries>
		<amn:topics>
			<amn:id name="Censorship and Freedom of Expression">2094</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Detention">2077</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Disappearances">2120</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Economic, Social and Cultural Rights">2087</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Penal Institutions">2080</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Press Freedom">2095</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Unlawful Detention">2078</amn:id>
		</amn:topics>
		<amn:resource-types>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2143</amn:id>
		</amn:resource-types>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.amnesty.org/en/?p=142450</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In the run up to the general elections in Nicaragua, scheduled for 7 November, Amnesty International, the Center for Justice and International Law (CEJIL), CIVICUS; Human Rights Watch, the International Institute on Race, Equality and Human Rights, the Washington Office on Latin American, the World Organisation Against Torture, People in Need, the International Network of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/nicaragua-five-reasons-why-elections-do-not-guarantee-the-exercise-of-human-rights/">Nicaragua: International organizations set out five reasons why elections do not guarantee the exercise of human rights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the run up to the general elections in Nicaragua, scheduled for 7 November, Amnesty International, the Center for Justice and International Law (CEJIL), CIVICUS; Human Rights Watch, the International Institute on Race, Equality and Human Rights, the Washington Office on Latin American, the World Organisation Against Torture, People in Need, the International Network of Human Rights, and Women&#8217;s Link Worldwide, have issued a manifesto setting out five reasons that explain how the coming general elections will be held in the context of serious restrictions on civil and political liberties.</p>



<p>In <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/amr43/4945/2021/en/">the joint document</a>, the signatory organizations highlight the intensification of repression and harassment of dissident voices, as part of a context in which the conditions do not exist for holding elections that guarantee the exercise of rights.</p>



<p>The Nicaraguan government has tried to eliminate and discourage electoral competition through arbitrary detention, enforced disappearance and the prosecution of opponents and presidential candidates, as well as by creating obstacles to the candidacy of the main opposition parties. It has also harassed and intimidated the press and violated political rights, all with the collaboration of the legislative and judicial powers. The intensification of harassment, in addition to the repeated abusive use of force and impunity, have increased concerns about human rights violations in the context of social mobilization.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For these reasons, the organizations, are calling on the international community, multilateral organizations and international human rights organizations to redouble their efforts and endeavours to end the human rights crisis.</p>



<p><strong>For more information or to arrange an interview, contact Duncan Tucker: </strong><a href="mailto:duncan.tucker@amnesty.org"><strong>duncan.tucker@amnesty.org</strong></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/nicaragua-five-reasons-why-elections-do-not-guarantee-the-exercise-of-human-rights/">Nicaragua: International organizations set out five reasons why elections do not guarantee the exercise of human rights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
      
      
      
      		<item>
		<title>Venezuela: ICC Prosecutor’s primary consideration in opening an investigation must be timely and effective justice for victims</title>
		<link>https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/venezuela-icc-prosecutors-primary-consideration-opening-investigation-must-be-timely-effective-justice-victims/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amnesty International]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 18:55:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<amn:content-types>
			<amn:id name="News">1148</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2181</amn:id>
		</amn:content-types>
		<amn:countries>
			<amn:id name="Americas">1699</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="South America">1707</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Venezuela">1804</amn:id>
		</amn:countries>
		<amn:topics>
			<amn:id name="Human Rights Defenders and Activists">2121</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Impunity">2102</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="International Justice">2100</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="International Organizations">2122</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Justice Systems">2099</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="War Crimes and Crimes Against Humanity">2066</amn:id>
		</amn:topics>
		<amn:resource-types>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2143</amn:id>
		</amn:resource-types>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.amnesty.org/en/?p=142594</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In&#160;response to&#160;the&#160;Office of the Prosecutor of the&#160;International Criminal Court&#160;(ICC)&#160;announcing that it is&#160;opening an investigation into alleged crimes against humanity committed in Venezuela, Erika Guevara-Rosas, Americas Director at Amnesty International said:&#160; “The International Criminal Court&#160;has finally recognized the urgency of investigating the crimes against humanity that&#160;multiple human rights organizations, including Amnesty International,&#160;have&#160;documented and&#160;denounced for years in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/venezuela-icc-prosecutors-primary-consideration-opening-investigation-must-be-timely-effective-justice-victims/">Venezuela: ICC Prosecutor’s primary consideration in opening an investigation must be timely and effective justice for victims</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In&nbsp;response to&nbsp;the&nbsp;Office of the Prosecutor of the&nbsp;International Criminal Court&nbsp;(ICC)&nbsp;announcing that it is&nbsp;opening an investigation into alleged crimes against humanity committed in Venezuela, Erika Guevara-Rosas, Americas Director at Amnesty International said:&nbsp;</p>



<p>“The International Criminal Court&nbsp;has finally recognized the urgency of investigating the crimes against humanity that&nbsp;multiple human rights organizations, including Amnesty International,&nbsp;have&nbsp;documented and&nbsp;denounced for years in Venezuela. The Office of the Prosecutor must fully investigate the atrocities committed&nbsp;against the Venezuelan people, pursuing cases against those who bear the greatest responsibility for crimes against humanity.&#8221;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The ICC Prosecutor has announced the conclusion of&nbsp;his Office’s preliminary examination in Venezuela –&nbsp;which it had opened in 2018 – with a determination that a full investigation is warranted. The Office of the Prosecutor had previously found that crimes against humanity have been committed in Venezuela&nbsp;under Nicolas Maduro’s government,&nbsp;since at least 2017, including arbitrary detentions, use of torture and other cruel, inhuman and degrading treatment,&nbsp;rape and other forms of&nbsp;sexual violence, as well as persecution.&nbsp;</p>


<blockquote class="blockquote is-lined" style='quotes:"“" "”" "‘" "’"'><p>The Office of the Prosecutor must fully investigate the atrocities committed against the Venezuelan people</p>
<cite>-Erika Guevara-Rosas, Americas Director at Amnesty International</cite></blockquote>


<p>In a public announcement, Prosecutor Khan and President Maduro explained that they had agreed to a “Letter of Understanding”. Prosecutor Khan also highlighted the importance of “positive complementarity” in his approach to the Venezuela investigation.</p>



<p>“This&nbsp;is the first ICC investigation into a country in the&nbsp;Americas.&nbsp;To be effective, the ICC must commence as soon as possible, and should impartially investigate those most responsible for the&nbsp;systematic&nbsp;policy of repression and social control&nbsp;in&nbsp;Venezuela,&nbsp;since at least 2014, as noted by the United Nations’&nbsp;Fact-Finding Mission in&nbsp;its reports in&nbsp;September 2020&nbsp;and September 2021,” added Erika Guevara-Rosas.</p>



<p>“While a cooperative approach to investigations would be desirable, the Prosecutor should listen to calls from victims who are yet to see justice and recognise that his Office’s intervention is urgently needed for prompt and effective investigations of crimes against humanity in Venezuela. Although the ‘principle of complementarity’ urges the Prosecutor to call on Venezuelan authorities to carry out independent and impartial domestic investigations in Venezuela, he must not be deferential to state proceedings at all costs. In particular, when states are not genuinely willing or able to investigate and prosecute crimes under international law themselves &#8211; including investigations into those at senior levels or most responsible.”</p>



<p>“Above all, the Prosecutor’s approach must ensure that the rights to justice of victims and survivors of human rights violations in the country are respected and fulfilled by the Court and in Venezuela. It is paramount that human rights defenders who have sought justice at the ICC should be protected against any reprisals.”</p>



<p><strong>For more information or to arrange an interview, contact Duncan Tucker: </strong><a href="mailto:duncan.tucker@amnesty.org"><strong>duncan.tucker@amnesty.org</strong></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/11/venezuela-icc-prosecutors-primary-consideration-opening-investigation-must-be-timely-effective-justice-victims/">Venezuela: ICC Prosecutor’s primary consideration in opening an investigation must be timely and effective justice for victims</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
     

	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
			<item>
		<title>Ethiopia: Sweeping emergency powers and alarming rise in online hate speech as Tigray conflict escalates</title>
		<link>https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2021/11/ethiopia-sweeping-emergency-powers-and-alarming-rise-in-online-hate-speech-as-tigray-conflict-escalates/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amnesty International]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 10:16:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<amn:content-types>
			<amn:id name="News">1148</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2181</amn:id>
		</amn:content-types>
		<amn:countries>
			<amn:id name="Africa">1698</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Ethiopia">1749</amn:id>
		</amn:countries>
		<amn:topics>
			<amn:id name="Armed Conflict">2063</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Armed Groups">2064</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Discrimination">2081</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="Terrorism">2065</amn:id>
			<amn:id name="War Crimes and Crimes Against Humanity">2066</amn:id>
		</amn:topics>
		<amn:resource-types>
			<amn:id name="Press Release">2143</amn:id>
		</amn:resource-types>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.amnesty.org/en/?p=142624</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ethiopia is teetering on the brink of a human rights and humanitarian catastrophe, Amnesty International warned today, amid worrying developments linked to the escalating Tigray conflict. On 4 November the Ethiopian government granted itself sweeping new emergency powers which arbitrarily restrict human rights and threaten the independence of the judiciary. Meanwhile there has been an [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2021/11/ethiopia-sweeping-emergency-powers-and-alarming-rise-in-online-hate-speech-as-tigray-conflict-escalates/">Ethiopia: Sweeping emergency powers and alarming rise in online hate speech as Tigray conflict escalates</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Ethiopia is teetering on the brink of a human rights and humanitarian catastrophe, Amnesty International warned today, amid worrying developments linked to the escalating Tigray conflict.</p>



<p>On 4 November the Ethiopian government granted itself sweeping new emergency powers which arbitrarily restrict human rights and threaten the independence of the judiciary.<br><br>Meanwhile there has been an alarming rise in social media posts advocating ethnic violence, and government officials have implored civilians to take up arms against the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF) and the Oromo Liberation Army (OLA), which have recently joined forces against the central government.</p>



<p>“The dire humanitarian and human rights crisis which began one year ago in Tigray has been spilling into other areas of the country. To stop the situation spiraling out of control, the Ethiopian authorities must urgently take serious action to ensure human rights and international humanitarian law are respected,” said Deprose Muchena, Regional Director for East and Southern Africa at Amnesty International.&nbsp;</p>






<blockquote class="blockquote is-lined" style='quotes:"“" "”" "‘" "’"'><p>The dire humanitarian and human rights crisis which began one year ago in Tigray has been spilling into other areas of the country. To stop the situation spiraling out of control, the Ethiopian authorities must urgently take serious action to ensure human rights and international humanitarian law are respected</p>
<cite>Deprose Muchena, Regional Director for East and Southern Africa at Amnesty International</cite></blockquote>


<h2 id="h-state-of-emergency"><strong>State of Emergency</strong></h2>



<p>Ethiopia’s federal parliament adopted a state of emergency on 4 November, exactly a year after armed conflict with the TPLF began.</p>



<p>The emergency proclamation is overly broad, since it extends to the entire country and restricts human rights that cannot be limited or suspended under any circumstances according to international law.</p>



<p>For example, it allows authorities to arrest anyone without a warrant if there is “reasonable suspicion” of cooperation with “terrorist groups”, and to detain them without judicial review for as long as the proclamation is in place, currently for six months.</p>



<p>This could have a particularly worrying impact on human rights defenders and journalists. The emergency proclamation allows for NGO and media outlet licenses to be suspended or cancelled if they are suspected of providing direct or indirect material or moral support to “terrorist organizations” – terms which are ill-defined and open to broad interpretation.&nbsp;<br><br>Earlier this year, Amnesty International documented <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/07/ethiopia-end-arbitrary-detentions-of-tigrayans-activists-and-journalists-in-addis-ababa-and-reveal-whereabouts-of-unaccounted-detainees/">mass round-ups and arbitrary detentions of Tigrayans</a>, including journalists and a human rights activist, whom the government claimed had ties to the TPLF, which is designated as a terrorist group by the Ethiopian federal government.</p>



<p>The emergency proclamation also allows for the prohibition of any form of expression opposed to “the operation of the Emergency Operation and the purpose of the Proclamation” and poses challenges to the independence of the judiciary.<br><br>“The sweeping nature of this state of emergency is a blueprint for escalating human rights violations, including arbitrary detention, particularly of human rights defenders, journalists, minorities and government critics. And it puts detainees at heightened risk of torture and other ill-treatment,” said Deprose Muchena.</p>



<h2 id="h-civilians-asked-to-take-up-arms"><strong>Civilians asked to take up arms</strong></h2>



<p>In another worrying development, government officials in several Ethiopian regions have recently implored civilians to take up arms to repel the ongoing TPLF offensive.</p>



<p>In the capital Addis Ababa, government officials have asked civilians to organize to safeguard their surroundings, and to register arms or hand them to neighbours if they are unable to use them themselves. Similar calls to arms have been echoed by the Amhara, Oromia and Somali regional governments.</p>



<p>This call to arms puts people’s rights and even lives at risk by encouraging the establishment of untrained and unaccountable militias. Such groups already have committed war crimes in this conflict, including unlawful killings, rape and other sexual violence targeting people on the basis of their ethnicity.</p>



<h2 id="h-rise-in-online-hate-speech"><strong>Rise in online hate speech</strong></h2>



<p>On 3 November, <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-59154984">Facebook removed</a> a post by Ethiopia’s Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed, stating it had violated the platform’s policies against inciting violence.<br><br>However, Amnesty International has noted a significant rise in other recent social media posts inciting violence and using ethnic slurs against Tigrayans, some of which have gone unchecked. According to analysis from a local human rights organization, influential people such as journalists and political figures were among those sharing the posts, and social media platforms were slow to remove them.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Ethiopian authorities have an obligation to prohibit advocacy of hatred that constitutes incitement to hostility, discrimination or violence. The authorities must urgently denounce any statements, online or otherwise, which advocate violence against a specific ethnic group. Given the rising political and ethnic tension in Ethiopia, social media companies also have a responsibility to rapidly scale up their content moderation efforts, and ensure that the algorithms behind their platforms are not fueling advocacy of violence,” said Deprose Muchena.</p>






<blockquote class="blockquote is-lined" style='quotes:"“" "”" "‘" "’"'><p>Given the rising political and ethnic tension in Ethiopia, social media companies also have a responsibility to rapidly scale up their content moderation efforts, and ensure that the algorithms behind their platforms are not fueling advocacy of violence.</p>
<cite>Deprose Muchena</cite></blockquote>


<h2 id="h-civilians-at-risk-amid-escalation">Civilians at risk amid escalation</h2>



<p>Amnesty International reiterated its call on all parties to the conflict in Ethiopia to respect international humanitarian law and protect civilians. Leaders on all sides must also renounce incitement to violence against individuals based on their ethnicity.</p>



<p>Since the conflict in Tigray began in November 2020, the organization has documented war crimes by Ethiopia National Defence Forces, Eritrean forces, and Amhara forces, and has been documenting an increasing number of allegations of war crimes by the TPLF. The Oromo Liberation Army (OLA) has repeatedly been implicated in serious human rights abuses, mainly attacks targeting ethnic Amhara minorities in Western Oromia.<br><br>Violations by the warring parties have included <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/press-release/2021/02/ethiopia-eritrean-troops-massacre-of-hundreds-of-axum-civilians-may-amount-to-crime-against-humanity/">massacres</a>, <a href="https://citizenevidence.org/2021/04/09/geolocation-mahibere-dego/">extrajudicial killings of captives</a> and <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2021/08/ethiopia-troops-and-militia-rape-abduct-women-and-girls-in-tigray-conflict-new-report/">sexual violence</a> targeting women and girls. Barriers to access for humanitarian organizations to areas affected by the conflict and attacks targeting aid workers and facilities have greatly worsened the dire humanitarian situation resulting from the conflict. </p>






<blockquote class="blockquote is-lined" style='quotes:"“" "”" "‘" "’"'><p>African leaders and other international actors with influence must make clear to all the parties in Ethiopia that they must step back from the brink, protect civilians, end incitement, allow unhindered humanitarian access and monitoring, and respect human rights. </p>
<cite>Deprose Muchena</cite></blockquote>


<p>“African leaders and other international actors with influence must make clear to all the parties in Ethiopia that they must step back from the brink, protect civilians, end incitement, allow unhindered humanitarian access and monitoring, and respect human rights,” said Deprose Muchena.&nbsp;<br><br>“The parties must understand that those responsible for war crimes and other violations will be held accountable.”<br></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2021/11/ethiopia-sweeping-emergency-powers-and-alarming-rise-in-online-hate-speech-as-tigray-conflict-escalates/">Ethiopia: Sweeping emergency powers and alarming rise in online hate speech as Tigray conflict escalates</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.amnesty.org/en">Amnesty International</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	
	
</channel>
</rss>
